Guide to the Lady Pleasance Reeve Smith, Original Letters
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
"Original letters"
1793-1857
OSBORN D148
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.31
(3 volumes)
Autograph MSS. Collection of letters assembled by Lady Smith from her correspondence and that of her husband, Sir James Edward Smith (1759-1828); before each section of letters, she provides a brief biographical sketch of the authors represented in those letters; the third volume contains mainly letters reacting to her husband's death and to her Memoir and Correspondence of the Late Sir J.E. Smith; collection touches on many aspects of the Smiths' interests, personal and public, scientific and literary; it illustrates their many friendships, especially with the family of William Roscoe (1753-1831) and the Holkham literary circle; especially interesting are the discussions of gardening and concerning the Linnean Society of England; on the whole it provides a well-rounded picture of Norfolk society and literature from the late 18th century to the mid 19th century; the collection includes several MS and printed poems.
Smith, Pleasance (Reeve), Lady Smith, 1773-1877
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a complete inventory of the contents of Osborn d148. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
Country life -- Great Britain; Families -- England -- Domestic relations; Gardening; Women authors; Norfolk (England) -- Social life and customs -- 18th century; Norfolk (England) -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Smith, James Edward, 1759-1828; Smith, Pleasance (Reeve), Lady Smith, 1773-1877
- Osborn Shelves d148
  - BAKEWELL, MR.
    - AL (in 3rd person) to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1833 May 8 (Box 3)
      Scope and Contents
      n.p.
      3 p.; 18 x 11 cm.
      Thanks her for sending a copy of the
      "Memoirs of Sir James Edward Smith"
      (1759-1828).
      d 148/3/51
  - BATHURST, HENRY, BP. OF NORWICH, 1744-1837
    - 3 ALS to Sir James Edward Smith, (1759-1828), 1815-24 (Box 1)
      1815 Jan 31, 1824, and n.d.
      various places
      3 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      About his son's marriage, William
      Roscoe (1753-1831), and a bill to
      grant privileges to Unitarianism.
      d 148/1/6-8
  - BALCH, K. M.
    - ALS to the Rev. William Fitt Drake, [1833] Jan 28 (Box 3)
      3 p.; 19 x 11 cm.
      Concerns his portrayal in the
      d 148/3/48
  - BALCH, K. M.
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1833 Feb 5 (Box 3)
      3 p.; 22 x 19 cm.
      Concerns the "Memoirs of Sir James
      Edward Smith" (1759-1828).
      d 148/3/49
  - BOOTT, FRANCIS, 1792-1862
    - 3 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1828-1833 (Box 3)
      8 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      About the death and the "Memoirs" of
      Sir James Edward Smith (1759-1828),
      the death and career of Lord Byron
      (George Gordon Noel Byron, 6th baron,
      1788-1824), the writings of the
      ancient author Virgil, etc.
      d 148/3/11, 34, 44
  - BOOTT, MARY (HARDCASTLE)
    - 2 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1832 (Box 3)
      1832 Nov 5 and Nov 11
      Both letters primarily discuss the
      (1759-1828) and contemporary
      reaction to the work.
      d 148/3/34, 35
  - CALDWELL, ANDREW, 1733-1808
    - 5 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1799-1808 (Box 2)
      1799-1808, various dates
      18 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      About his travels in England,
      plants, news of friends and family,
      the house of Samuel Johnson
      (1709-1784), the poetry of Robert
      Burns (1759-1796) and Allan Ramsay
      (1686-1758), his health, etc.
      d 148/2/21-25
  - CASAMAJOR, HARRIET (EAST), D. 1831
    - 4 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1803-1830 (Box 2)
      1803-1830 various dates
      11 p.; various sizes
      Mainly on news of her family.
      d 148/2/9, 16, 18-19
  - CORRIE, S.
    - 4 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1832-1833 (Box 3)
      Woodville
      16 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      The letters describe Mrs. Corrie's
      reactions, enthusiastic, to the
      (1759-1828); she also discusses Mrs.
      Corrie's failing health.
      d 148/3/27, 36, 40, 41
  - CRABBE, GEORGE, 1785-1857
    - 2 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1834 (Box 1)
      1834 Mar 17 and Apr 30
      Pucklechurch
      6 p.; 22 x 18 cm.
      Reminisces about his father, the
      poet George Crabbe (1754-1832),
      various places they lived, and old
      friends.
      d 148/1/14-15
  - CULLUM, SIR THOMAS GERY, 1741-1831
    - ALS to [William Fitt] Drake, 1828 Mar 24 (Box 3)
      Bury
      1 p.; 25 x 20 cm.
      Sends condolences on the death of
      Sir James Edward Smith (1759-1828).
      d 148/3/6
  - CULLUM, SIR THOMAS GERY, 1741-1831
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1828 Apr 3 (Box 3)
      Concerns the effects of the death of
      Sir James Edward Smith (1759-1828)
      on the Linnean Society, etc.
      d 148/3/15
  - DAVY, MARTIN, 1763-1839
    - ALS to William Fitt Drake, 1828 Mar 21 (Box 3)
      Caius Lodge
      2 p.; 22 x 18 cm.
      d 148/3/3
  - DERBY, EDWARD SMITH STANLEY, 13TH EARL OF, 1775-1851
    - 2 ALS to William Fitt Drake, 1828 (Box 3)
      1828 Mar 19 and Apr 1
      London
      4 p.; 23 x 19 cm. and 18 x 13 cm.
      About the death of Sir James Edward
      Smith (1759-1828).
      d 148/3/2, 13
  - EAST, EASTLY CLAYTON
    - 1 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1831 Apr 4 (Box 2)
      Hallplace
      2 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      On the death of his aunt, Harriet
      (East) Casamajor (d. 1831).
      d 148/2/20
  - EAST, HANNAH (CASAMAJOR), LADY EAST, D. 1810
    - 12 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1799-1809 (Box 2)
      1799-1809
      43 p.; various sizes
      Letters mainly provide news of
      daily activities of family members
      and friends.
      d 148/2/1-6, 8, 10-14
  - EAST, SIR WILLIAM, 1ST BART., 1738-1819
    - 2 ALS to Sir James Edward Smith (1759-1828) and 1 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1804-11 (Box 2)
      1804 Jul 25, 1810 Nov 16, 1811 Jan 24
      9 p.; various sizes
      d 148/2/7, 15, 17
  - ERSKINE, THOMAS ERSKINE, 1ST BARON, 1750-1823
    - ALS to Sir James Edward Smith (1759-1828), 1810 Jun 13 (Box 1)
      Upper Grovesnor Street
      1 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      Looks forward to meeting him.
      d 148/1/5
  - ESTLIN, JOHN BISHOP, 1785-1855
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1828 Mar 28 (Box 3)
      Bristol
      4 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      d 148/3/9
  - FORSTER, EDWARD, 1765-1849
    - ALS to William Fitt Drake, 1828 Mar 19 (Box 3)
      1 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      d 148/3/1
  - FOUNTAINE, ANDREW
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1828 Apr 9 (Box 3)
      Lynn
      d 148/3/20
  - FOX, CHARLES JAMES, 1749-1806
    - ALS to Sir James Edward Smith (1759-1828), 1798 Jul 19 (Box 1)
      St. Anne's Hill
      1 p.; 24 x 19 cm.
      d 148/1/3
  - HARDWICKE, THOMAS
    - 2 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1830-34 (Box 1)
      1830 Aug 11 and 1834 Nov 16
      Lambeth
      7 p.; 24 x 19 cm. and 23 x 19 cm.
      The first letter renews
      correspondence between the two and
      discusses prominent naturalists,
      such as Nathaniel Wallich
      (1786-1854); the second discusses
      the author's recent ailments.
      d 148/1/12, 13
  - HORNBLOWER, JANE ELIZABETH (ROSCOE), 1797-1853
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1828 Mar 28 (Box 3)
      Lodge Lane
      2 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      Sends her father's condolences on
      the death of Sir James Edward Smith
      d 148/3/10
  - JOHNES, JANE (JOHNES)
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), [1828?] Nov 16 (Box 3)
      Hill Court Near Exeter
      1 p.; 22 x 19 cm.
      and explains that her husband burned
      his correspondence with Sir James.
      d 148/3/24
  - LAMBERT, AYLMER BOURKE, 1761-1842
    - ALS to William Fitt Drake, 1828 Apr 1 (Box 3)
      d 148/3/12
  - LAMBERT, AYLMER BOURKE, 1761-1842
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), [1832 Dec] 27 (Box 3)
      Thanks her for Christmas dinner
      sends news of the Linnean Society
      d 148/3/39
  - LEICESTER, THOMAS WILLIAM COKE, EARL OF, 1752-1842
    - 5 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1822-1828 (Box 2–3)
      1822-1828 various dates
      On the birth of his sons and on the
      death of Sir James Edward Smith
      (1759-1855).
      d 148/2/34, 36, 39; d 148/3/4, 16
  - LOMBE, EDWARD, CA. 1800-1852
    - 2 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), [1828 Mar] (Box 3)
      [1828 Mar] and n.d.
      6 p.; 18 x 11 and 23 x 19 cm.
      The first letter (148/3/8) discusses
      his present health conditions and
      thanks Lady Smith for having sent
      him a copy of the "Memoirs of Sir
      James Edward Smith" (1759-1828)
      attached to this item is an extract
      written by her husband about Mr.
      Lombe which Lady Smith copied; the
      second letter (148/3/23) sends his
      respects.
      d 148/3/8, 23
  - MARTIN, L.
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), [1831 or later] (Box 3)
      4 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      Compliments Lady Smith, whom the
      author addresses as "My dear Aunt,"
      on the "Memoirs of Sir James Edward
      Smith" (1759-1828).
      d 148/3/31
  - MASTER, JANE
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1816 Jan 3 (Box 2)
      The Abbey
      4 p.; 18 x 11 cm.
      Thanks Lady Smith for concern over
      her mother's health following an
      accident.
      d 148/2/43
  - MASTER, MARY (PETTY), D. 1819
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1815 Nov 16 (Box 2)
      Discusses their recent visit and
      other family news.
      d 148/2/42
  - MASTER, MR. AND MRS.
    - AL (in third person) to Mrs. Reeve, n.d. (Box 2)
      2 p.; 18 x 11 cm.
      Reply to an invitation from Mrs.
      Reeve.
      d 148/2/41
  - MATON, WILLIAM GEORGE, 1774-1835
    - 2 ALS to William Fitt Drake, 1828 (Box 3)
      1828 Mar 22 and Apr 2
      8 p.; 22 x 18 and 18 x 13 cm.
      d 148/3/5, 14
  - MENZIES, ARCHIBALD, 1754-1842
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1832 Dec 14 (Box 3)
      3 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      Praises her "Memoir of Sir James
      d 148/3/38
  - MITFORD, JOHN, 1781-1859
    - 31 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 4 ALS to [?his publisher] and 1 ALS to [Mrs. Clarke], 1835-58 (Box 1, Box 3)
      1835-1858 various dates
      Benhall, Sloane Street, etc.
      99 p.; various sizes
      About his poetry and work on Thomas
      Gray (1716-1771), his friendship
      with Samuel Rogers (1763-1855), Lady
      Smith's memoir of her husband (Sir
      James Edward Smith, 1759-1828),
      literary subjects, gardening, his
      travels, friends, etc.
      with 20 p.; also with 20 p.
      of poetry from the "Gentleman's
      Magazine".
      d 148/1/16-50; d 148/3/47
  - MORLEY, FRANCES (TALBOT) PARKER, COUNTESS OF, 1786-1857
    - 3 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1804 (Box 2)
      1804 Jan 10, Aug 20, Dec 14
      Bath
      14 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      Discusses her daily activities, her
      acquaintance and sends news of
      mutual friends.
      d 148/2/44-46
  - MORLLICH, A.
    - ALS to Mrs. [S.] Corrie, n.d. (Box 3)
      Comments on the "Memoirs of Sir
      which Mrs. Corrie had sent; also
      comments on the health of Mrs.
      Corrie.
      d 148/3/43
  - NOAILLES, PHILIPPE DE, PRINCE DE POIX, 1752-1819
    - ALS to Sir James Edward Smith (1759-1828), [1800] May 3 (Box 1)
      Great Marylebone St.
      Thanks Smith for his kindness during
      the author's visit to England.
      d 148/1/4
  - OPIE, AMELIA (ALDERSON), 1769-1853
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1836 Dec 11 (Box 2)
      3 p.; 25 x 20 cm.
      About the French writer, Alphonse de
      Lamartine (1790-1869) and his family.
      d 148/2/47
  - PLATT, THOMAS
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1832 Nov 12 (Box 3)
      Thanks her for sending the "Memoirs
      of Sir James Edward Smith"
      d 148/3/37
  - RAMMOHUN, ROY, RAJA, 1772?-1833
    - 2 ALS to Sir James Edward Smith (1759-1828), 1832 and n.d. (Box 1)
      1832 May 21 and n.d.
      The first letter expresses his hopes
      of visiting the Smiths in the near
      future, and the second thanks Smith
      for an invitation.
      d 148/1/10
  - ROSCOE, WILLIAM CALDWELL, 1823-1859
    - "M[argaret] S[andback]": MS copy by Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1852 (Box 1)
      Havodunos
      1 p.; 11 x 18 cm.
      A poem written in honor of Margaret
      (Roscoe) Sandback (ca. 1812-1852).
      d 148/1/51
  - ROSCOE, WILLIAM CALDWELL, 1823-1859
    - "Lines to be placed under the portrait of the Rt. Revd. Dr. Henry Bathurst, Lord Bishop of Norwich [1744-1837], at Holkham:" MS copy by Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877) (Box 2)
      d 148/2/38
  - ROSCOE, WILLIAM, 1753-1831
    - 1 ALS and 1 LS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1828-30 (Box 3)
      1828 Dec 16 and 1830 Feb 6
      About botany, the Linnean Society
      and the death of Sir James Edward
      One letter (148/3/22) is partly
      transcribed by his son, Henry Roscoe
      (1800-1836), and the other (148/3/25)
      is wholly written by "T.E.R." [Thomas
      Roscoe? (1791-1871)].
      d 148/3/22, 25
  - SANDBACK, MARGARET (ROSCOE), CA. 1812-1852
    - 10 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1843-1851 (Box 1)
      The Cottage and Havodonus
      60 p.; various sizes
      Various reflections on her own works
      and those of friends.
      d 148/1/52-61
  - SCHUTZ, SUSAN ELIZABETH
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1832 Oct 9 (Box 3)
      Gillingham Hall
      5 p.; 18 x 11 and 23 x 18 cm.
      Thanks her for her present of the
      (1759-1828) and sends news of common
      friends and acquaintances.
      d 148/3/32
  - SMITH, EDWARD JAMES
    - 2 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1828-33 (Box 3)
      1828 Sep 20 and 1833 Sep 8
      6 p.; 25 x 20 cm.
      The first letter (148/3/21) sends
      his condolences on the death of his
      uncle, Sir James Edward Smith
      (1759-1828), and the second
      (148/3/52) discusses the memoirs his
      aunt has sent him.
      d 148/3/21, 52
  - SMITH, FRANCES
    - 2 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1828 and n.d. (Box 3)
      1828 Apr 8 and n.d.
      6 p.; 19 x 11 cm. and 13 x 10 cm.
      The first letter (148/3/19) sends
      condolences on the death of Sir
      James Edward Smith (1759-1828) and
      the second (148/3/46) comments on
      the "Memoirs" of the late Sir James
      which she had heard read.
      Women Writers.
      d 148/3/19, 46
  - SMITH, PLEASANCE (REEVE), LADY SMITH, 1773-1877
    - AL (copy, incomplete) to William Smyth (1765-1849), n.d. (Box 1)
      3 p.; 26 x 20 cm.
      The introduction to the copy of
      letter reads: "The following was a
      portion of a letter I sent to
      Professor Smyth on finding he had
      introduced Dr. Priestley [Joseph
      Priestley (1733-1804)] in his
      Evidences as one of the defenders of
      Christianity. His name having been
      unjustly slandered. I was gratified
      that the professor had vindicated
      his injured memory."
      d 148/1/65
  - SMITH, WILLIAM, 1756-1835
    - 3 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1828-33
      1828 Apr 6, 1830 Mar 18, 1833 Feb 4
      10 p.; various sizes
      The first letter (148/3/18) sends
      his condolences on the death of Sir
      James Edward Smith (1759-1828); the
      second (148/3/26) concerns
      correspondence which he has yet to
      look over; and the third (148/3/45)
      concerns the "Memoirs" of Sir James.
      d 148/3/18, 26, 45
  - SMYTH, WILLIAM, 1765-1849
    - 2 ALS and 1 AL to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1845 and n.d. (Box 1)
      [1845] May 27 and n.d.
      Norwich
      About his lectures and books which
      she has read and praised; about
      Joseph Priestley (1733-1804) and
      Jean-Jacques Rousseau (1712-1778).
      d 148/1/62-64
  - SOUTHWELL, M. TRAFFORD
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1832 Oct 8 (Box 3)
      Wroxham
      Thanks her for the gift of the
      "Memoirs of Sir James Edward
      d 148/3/30
  - STANHOPE, LADY ELIZABETH WILHELMINA (COKE), D. 1873
    - 12 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), various dates (Box 2–3)
      [Before 1816] - 1828 various dates
      48 p.; various sizes
      d 148/2/26-33, 35, 37, 40
      d 148/3/17
  - SWAINSON, MARY
    - ALS to Mrs. [S.] Corrie, [no year] Nov 30 (Box 3)
      d 148/3/42
  - TURNER, DAWSON, 1775-1858
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1832 Oct 8 (Box 3)
      Yarmouth
      2 p.; 25 x 20 cm.
      On her the gift of the "Memoirs of
      Sir James Edward Smith" (1759-1828).
      d 148/3/29
  - WALLICH, NATHANIEL, 1786-1854
    - 2 ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1829-32 (Box 1, Box 3)
      1829 Dec 19 and 1832 Oct 1
      8 p.; 25 x 20 cm. and 23 x 19 cm.
      The first letter concerns the death
      of Sir James Edward Smith
      (1759-1828), his current work,
      friends, etc.; the second letter is
      included in a letter of Francis
      Boott.
      d 148/1/9; d 148/3/28
  - WATT, MARTHA (ELLIS), D 1795
    - 2 ALS to [Sir James Edward] Smith (1759-1828), 1793-94 (Box 1)
      1793 May 9 and 1794 Jun 23
      Northau Place
      5 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      The first letter discusses material
      she sent to Smith for perusal and the
      second praises Smith's method of
      writing natural history.
      d 148/1/1,2
  - YOUNGE, W.
    - ALS to Pleasance (Reeve) Smith, Lady Smith (1773-1877), 1832 Oct 25 (Box 3)
      Sheffield
      d 148/3/33
  - [ILLEGIBLE SIGNATURE]
    - ALS to William Fitt Drake, 1828 Mar 28 (Box 3)
      Oxford
      d 148/3/7